Guide to the Aaron Baker Clark and Sarah Booth Clark Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Aaron Baker Clark and Sarah Booth Clark papers
1671-1971
1876-1925
WA MSS S-3437
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.67
(9 boxes)
The Aaron Baker Clark and Sarah Booth Clark Papers consist of biographical sketches, diaries, photographs, correspondence, and clippings that pertain to the missionary efforts of Episcopal minister Aaron Baker Clark and his wife, Sarah Booth Clark, relating to the Lakota people of the Rosebud Reservation in South Dakota. Also present are printed dictionaries and hymns in the Lakota dialect, 1889-1901, and other printed books on topics such as religion, history, geography and poetry, 1671-1971. Materials in the collection span the dates 1671 to 1971, with the bulk falling between 1876 and 1925.
Clark, Aaron B., Reverend
Clark, Sarah Booth
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Walter Clark and Mrs. David Clark on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2000-2014.
Arrangement
Organized into seven series: I. Biographical Sketches, undated. II. Aaron Baker Clark Diaries, 1876-1920. III. Sarah Booth Clark Diaries, 1910-1920. IV. Photographs, 1890-1925, undated. V. Correspondence, 1905-1915. VI. Clippings, undated. VII. Printed Volumes, 1671-1971.
Aaron Baker Clark (1855-1933)
Aaron Baker Clark (1855-1933) was an Episcopal minister from Westport, New York. He and his family lived on the Rosebud Reservation in South Dakota from 1889 to 1917, during which time he was a missionary.
He was born on January 27, 1855, to Aaron and Harriet Patience Clark. A graduate of the University of Vermont (class of 1876), he served as assistant principal of the Vermont Episcopal Institute (1874-1881) and as principal of the Vergennes graded schools (1881-1883). Following these positions, he later attended the General Theological Seminary of New York (1884-1886).
Clark became a deacon in the Protestant Episcopal Church in 1886 and served as rector of the Greenwith and Schuylerville parishes in the Diocese of Albany, New York, until 1888. In 1887, he was ordained into the priesthood by Bishop Doane of the Western New York District. He acted as the rector of St. Phillip's Episcopal Church in Belmont, New York, from 1888 to 1889.
Accepting a call to the Deanery of Niobrara in Dakota Territory to serve under Right Reverend William Hobart Hare, Clark—along with his wife, Sarah Booth Clark, and two sons, John and David—was received at the Rosebud Reservation in May 1889. The family's arrival came not long after the Indian Appropriations Act of 1889, which diminished the reach of the Rosebud Sioux lands.
From 1887 to 1889, the Rosebud Mission was without a permanent Episcopal missionary. During the Clark family's first year, the reservation consisted of fourteen chapels, churches, and stations. By this time, there were 260 communicants and 1,195 baptized Christians on Rosebud land. Conducting services in Sioux and English, Reverend Clark added to these figures throughout his time with the Lakota people.
Clark remained on the Rosebud Reservation for nearly three decades before undertaking direction of the Church at Hot Springs, South Dakota, in 1917. Five years later, he became missionary in charge at Gethsemane in Sisseton, South Dakota. Circa 1927, Clark served at the Good Shepherd Church in Wailukee on the island of Maui. He died on May 18, 1933, and was buried in Todd County, South Dakota.
Sarah Booth Clark (1861-1951)
Sarah Booth Clark was born in 1861 to Cyrus Austin Booth, a hardware merchant, and Sarah Booth White, both of Vergennes, Vermont. She married Aaron Baker Clark in 1886, in Vergennes.
The couple had three sons: John Booth (1887-1967), David William (1889-1970), and Hobart Hare (1894-1934).
Content Description
The Aaron Baker Clark and Sarah Booth Clark Papers consist of biographical sketches, diaries, photographs, correspondence, and clippings that pertain to the missionary efforts of Episcopal minister Aaron Baker Clark and his wife, Sarah Booth Clark, relating to the Lakota people of the Rosebud Reservation in South Dakota. Also present are printed dictionaries and hymns in the Lakota dialect, 1889-1901, and other printed books on topics such as religion, history, geography and poetry, 1671-1971. Materials in the collection span the dates 1671 to 1971, with the bulk falling between 1876 and 1925.
Spanning the entirety of the Clark family's time on the reservation, the papers chiefly contain accounts of life with the Lakota people. Diary entries from both Aaron and Sarah Clark note weather observations, illnesses, schoolwork, housework, travel, and births, deaths, and marriages. The diaries also record religious events on the reservation, specifically baptisms, confirmations, and convocations. In addition, there are several handwritten brief dictionaries (Dakota to English) and accounting records included.
The papers also contain photographs and correspondence. The former capture the Clark family and the Rosebud Reservation, while the latter reveal Reverend Clark's concern surrounding the funding of sectarian schools. Clippings in the collection provide context for Reverend Clark's letters.
Printed volumes in the collection consist of works belonging to the Clark family written both in English and Dakota. These materials range in content: dictionaries, religious texts, poetry, geography, history, chess, and romance.
Dakota language -- Dictionaries; Dakota language -- Texts; Indians of North America -- Education; Indians of North America -- Languages; Indians of North America -- South Dakota; Lakota dialect; Missionaries -- South Dakota -- 19th century; Rosebud Indian Reservation (S.D.); South Dakota -- Religion; Diaries -- United States; Photographs -- United States; Indians of North America -- Religion -- 19th century; Indians of North America -- Religion -- 20th Century; Lakota Indians -- Missions; South Dakota -- Religions life and customs; Missionaries -- South Dakota -- 20th Century; Episcopal Church -- Missions -- South Dakota; Episcopal Church -- Rosebud Mission; Clark, Walter Kinsley; Clark, David, Mrs.
- Biographical Sketches, undated; Series I
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains biographical sketches of Aaron Baker Clark and David William Clark.
  - Aaron Baker Clark, undated
    - Aaron Baker Clark (original Thermo-Fax), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Aaron Baker Clark (preservation copy), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - David William Clark, undated
    - David William Clark (original Thermo-Fax), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - David William Clark (preservation copy), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Aaron Baker Clark Diaries, 1876-1920; Series II
  Series II is arranged chronologically.
  Series II contains diaries kept by Aaron Baker Clark. His accounts focus primarily on his religious work. Entries document illness, travel, weather, schoolwork, and housework. Births, deaths, and marriages as well as baptisms, confirmations, and convocations are also recorded. In addition, there are several handwritten brief dictionaries (Dakota to English) and accounting records included.
  - Diary, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Diary, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Diaries, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Diaries, 1891-1892 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Diaries, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Diaries, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Diaries, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Diary, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Diaries, 1895-1896 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Diaries, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Diary, 1897-1898 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Diaries, 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Diaries, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Diaries, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Diaries, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Diaries, 1901-1903 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Diaries, 1903-1905 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Diaries, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Diaries, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Diaries, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Diaries, 1910-1912 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Diaries, 1912-1914 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Diary, 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Diary, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Diary, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Diaries, 1918-1920 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Sarah Booth Clark Diaries, 1910-1920; Series III
  Series III is arranged chronologically.
  Series III contains diaries kept by Sarah Booth Clark. Her accounts document cooking and housework, interactions with others on the Reservation, and the weather.
  - Diaries, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Diaries, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Diaries, 1912-1914 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Diaries, 1913-1915 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Diaries, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Diaries, 1917-1919 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Diaries, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Photographs, 1890-1925, undated; Series IV
  Series IV is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Series IV contains photographs of the Clark family as well as various members and residents of the Rosebud Reservation.
  - Aaron Baker Clark, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 61)
  - Sarah Booth Clark, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Clark family, 1890, 1913, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Clark home, 1917, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Fort Thompson, 1921, pre-1924 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Rosebud Homestead, Camp Remington, 1906-1909, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Rosebud Reservation, 1907-1925, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Rosebud Reservation, 1915, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Rosebud Reservation, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Correspondence, 1905-1915; Series V
  Series V is arranged chronologically.
  Series V contains correspondence (incoming and outgoing) with Aaron Baker Clark. Letters document concerns surrounding the use of tribal funds for Roman Catholic schools, the presence of sectarian insignia in federal schools, and conflicts between Roman Catholic teaching methods and Prostetantism.
  - Correspondence, 1905 April-1912 February (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, 1905 March 6 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, 1905 March 9 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, 1905 March 23-26 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence, 1906 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 62)
  - Correspondence, 1906, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 63)
  - Correspondence, 1910 November 5-22 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence, 1912 May-June (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence, 1914 July 29 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence, 1915 February 12-13 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Clippings, circa 1906, undated; Series VI
  Series VI is arranged chronologically.
  Series VI contains clippings pertaining to educational programs run by Roman Catholic missionaries.
  - Clippings, circa 1906 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 64)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Printed Volumes, 1671-1971; Series VII
  Series VII is arranged alphabetically by title of work.
  Series VII contains printed volumes belonging to the Clark family. Materials are both in English and Dakota and include dictionaries, religious texts, poetry, geography, history, a chess manual, and romance.
  - Apocrypha (Oxford University Press), undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Book of Common Prayer (New York: Megarey), 1820 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Compendium of Ancient Geography by Monsieur D'Anville (New York: McDermut and Arden), 1814 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Complete Concordance to the Holy Scriptures, by Alexander Cruden (New York: Dodd, Mead & co.), 1878 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Dakota odowan, hymns in the Dakota language (Riggs and Williamson), pre-1974 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - English-Dakota Dictionary (Williamson), 1901 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - History of Charles the 12th, King of Sweden, by Voltaire (Hartford: Andrus), 1825 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - The Holy Bible, Containing the Old and New Testaments, According to the Authorized Version; With Explanatory Notes, Practical Observations, and Copious Marginal References, by Thomas Scott, Rector of Aston Sanford, Bucks (Boston: Samuel E. Armstrong), 1827
    - Volume I, 1827 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Volume II, 1827 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Volume III, 1827 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Volume IV, 1827 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Volume V, 1827 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Volume VI, 1827 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Lalla Rookh, by Thomas Moore (New York: Hurd and Hougton), 1867 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Marache's Manual of Chess, by Napoleon Marache (New York: Dick and Fitzgerald), 1866 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - A New and Useful Concordance to the Holy Bible (London: R. Clark), 1671 (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - The New Testament (Oxford University Press), 1870 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Okodakiciye wakan tadowan kin hymnal, 1889 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - The Poems of Henry Wadsworth Longfellow (Boston: Houghton, Mifflin), 1881 (Box 9, Folder 73)
  - Sententiae Selectae, or a Collection of Miscellaneous Sentences, Divine, Moral, and Historical, in Prose and Verse, English and Latin, Excerpted from the Works of Many Learned and Judicious Authors, and Digested into Alphabetical Order, for the Use of Schools, by Edward Curray (London: Cobb), 1732 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - Sioux Dictionary (Grant), 1971 (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - The Works of Laurence Stern, Volume V (New York: Durrell), 1814 (Box 9, Folder 76)